What is going to be the future of learning?
ما هو مستقبل التعليم؟
I do have a plan,
أنا لدي خطة
but in order for me to tell you what that plan is,
و لكن قبل ان اطرح هذه الخطة
I need to tell you a little story,
علي ان احكي لكم قصة قصيرة
which kind of sets the stage.
لتوضيح الفكرة.
I tried to look at
لقد حاولت البحث
where did the kind of learning we do in schools,
عن مصدر نظام التعليم الذي
where did it come from?
نتلقاه اليوم و من أين اتى
And you can look far back into the past,
و يمكننا الذهاب بعيداً عبر التاريخ
but if you look at present-day schooling the way it is,
و لكن اذا نظرنا الى المدرسة في يومنا هذا
it's quite easy to figure out where it came from.
من السهل ان نعرف من اين اتت الفكرة.
It came from about 300 years ago,
أتت من حوالي 300 عام مضى
and it came from the last
و بالتحديد من اكبر و آخر
and the biggest of the empires on this planet. ["The British Empire"]
امبراطورية على هذا الكوكب (الامبراطورية البريطانية)
Imagine trying to run the show,
تخيل ان تكون الرأس المدبر
trying to run the entire planet,
محاولاً تشغيل هذا العالم،
without computers, without telephones,
من غير حواسيب او هواتف،
with data handwritten on pieces of paper,
بمعلومات مكتوبة يدوياً على ورق،
and traveling by ships.
مسافراً على سفن.
But the Victorians actually did it.
«الفكتوريون» نجحوا في تحقيق ذلك.
What they did was amazing.
و ما فعلوه كان مذهلاً.
They created a global computer
لقد صنعوا حاسوب عالمي
made up of people.
مصنوع من بشر.
It's still with us today.
و ما زال معنا اليوم.
It's called the bureaucratic administrative machine.
يسمى بالآلة البيروقراطية الادارية.
In order to have that machine running,
و حتى تعمل هذه الآلة،
you need lots and lots of people.
ستحتاج الى الكثير من البشر.
They made another machine to produce those people:
و لقد صنعوا آلة أخرى لإنتاج هؤلاء البشر:
the school.
المدرسة.
The schools would produce the people
المدرسة تنتج بشراً
who would then become parts of the
ليكونوا أجزاء من
bureaucratic administrative machine.
الآلة البيروقراطية الإدارية.
They must be identical to each other.
و لا بد ان يكونوا متطابقين.
They must know three things:
و يجب ان يعرفوا ثلاث اشياء:
They must have good handwriting, because the data is handwritten;
لديهم خط يدوي جيد، لأن المعلومات مكتوبة يدوياً،
they must be able to read;
القدرة على القراءة،
and they must be able to do multiplication,
و معرفة عمليات الحساب الرياضية
division, addition and subtraction in their head.
كالضرب والجمع والطرح و القسمة، بالعقل
They must be so identical that you could pick one up from New Zealand
لا بد ان يكونوا متطابقين بحيث يمكنك ان تأخذ فرداً
and ship them to Canada
من نيوزيلندا و شحنه الى كندا
and he would be instantly functional.
ليكون فعالاً، و فوراً.
The Victorians were great engineers.
كان الفكتوريين مهندسين بارعين.
They engineered a system that was so robust
لقد هندسوا نظام متين جداً
that it's still with us today,
يعمل حتى يومنا هذا،
continuously producing identical people
مواصلاً عملية انتاج بشر متطابقون
for a machine that no longer exists.
من أجل آلة لم تعد موجودة.
The empire is gone,
لقد ذهبت الامبراطورية،
so what are we doing with that design
فماذا نحن بفاعلين بهذا التصميم
that produces these identical people,
الذي ينتج بشراً متطابقون،
and what are we going to do next
و ماذا سنفعل بعد هذا
if we ever are going to do anything else with it?
اذا كنا لنستفيد بأي شكل كان من هذا التصميم؟
["Schools as we know them are obsolete"]
فكما نعرف، المدارس بالية.
So that's a pretty strong comment there.
و هذا تعليق قوي جداً.
I said schools as we know them now, they're obsolete.
لقد قلت ان المدارس كما نعرفها اليوم، بالية.
I'm not saying they're broken.
و لا أقول انها عاطلة.
It's quite fashionable to say that the education system's broken.
فمن السهل جداً قول ذلك، اي ان نظام التعليم معطل.
It's not broken. It's wonderfully constructed.
النظام لم يتعطل. و هو مبني بطريقة عجيبة.
It's just that we don't need it anymore. It's outdated.
و لكننا فقط لم نعد نحتاجه. لقد انتهت مدته.
What are the kind of jobs that we have today?
ما هي انواع الوظائف اليوم؟
Well, the clerks are the computers.
المحررين هم الحواسيب.
They're there in thousands in every office.
و هي بالآلاف في كل مكتب.
And you have people who guide those computers
و هناك اناس يقودون هذه الحواسيب
to do their clerical jobs.
لتقوم بإنتاج عملهم الكتابي.
Those people don't need to be able to write beautifully by hand.
و ليس عليهم ان يكتبوا بخطوط الايادي الجميلة.
They don't need to be able to multiply numbers in their heads.
لا يحتاجون الى حل المسائل الحسابية بعقولهم.
They do need to be able to read.
يحتاجون الى القدرة على القراءة.
In fact, they need to be able to read discerningly.
و في الحقيقة، يحتاجون القدرة على القراءة بإحساس و امعان.
Well, that's today, but we don't even know
حسنا، هذا بالنسبة لليوم و لكننا لا نعرف بعد
what the jobs of the future are going to look like.
كيف ستكون الوظائف في المستقبل.
We know that people will work from wherever they want,
نعرف ان الناس سيستطيعون العمل حيث يريدون
whenever they want, in whatever way they want.
في اي وقت و في اي مجال شاءوا.
How is present-day schooling going to prepare them
و لكن كيف تجهزهم المدرسة في يومنا هذا
for that world?
لذلك العالم؟
Well, I bumped into this whole thing completely by accident.
حسناً، لقد اصتدمت انا بهذا الموضوع بالصدفة كلياً.
I used to teach people how to write computer programs
كنت اعلم الناس كتابة برامج الحاسوب
in New Delhi, 14 years ago.
قبل 14 عاما في نيو دلهي.
And right next to where I used to work, there was a slum.
قريباً جداً من مكان عملي كانت هناك منطقة فقيرة.
And I used to think, how on Earth are those kids
و كنت اتساءل، يا ترى كيف سيمكن لهؤلاء الاطفال
ever going to learn to write computer programs?
تعلم كتابة برامج الحاسوب؟
Or should they not?
ام لا يجب عليهم ذلك؟
At the same time, we also had lots of parents,
و في نفس الوقت، كان هناك آباء كثيرين،
rich people, who had computers,
أغنياء، يمتلكون حواسيب،
and who used to tell me, "You know, my son,
و كانوا يقولون لي "هل تعلم، فإن ابني
I think he's gifted,
أظنه موهوب
because he does wonderful things with computers.
فهو يفعل اشياء رهيبة بالحاسوب.
And my daughter -- oh, surely she is extra-intelligent."
و ابنتي، اه، بالتأكيد لديها ذكاء عالي".. و الخ.
And so on. So I suddenly figured that,
و فجاءةَ تداركت
how come all the rich people are having
لماذا كل هذه المواهب و الذكاء
these extraordinarily gifted children?
فقط عند أطفال الاغنياء؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What did the poor do wrong?
ماذا فعل هؤلاء الفقراء؟
I made a hole in the boundary wall
صنعت فتحة في الحائط حول
of the slum next to my office,
المنطقة الفقيرة بالقرب من مكتبي،
and stuck a computer inside it just to see what would happen
و وضعت جهاز حاسوب هناك فقط لأرى ماذا سيحدث
if I gave a computer to children who never would have one,
اذا اعطيته لأطفال لم يرو حاسوباً من قبل،
didn't know any English, didn't know what the Internet was.
لا يعرفون الانجليزية و لا يعرفون ما هو الانترنت.
The children came running in.
تسارع الاطفال اليه
It was three feet off the ground, and they said, "What is this?"
و كان يعلو 3 اقدام فوق الارض و سألوا "ما هذا؟"
And I said, "Yeah, it's, I don't know."
و قلت "نعم، هذا، لا ادري"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They said, "Why have you put it there?"
سألوا "لماذا وضعته هنا؟"
I said, "Just like that."
قلت "هكذا فقط".
And they said, "Can we touch it?"I said, "If you wish to."
و سألوا "هل يمكن ان نلمسه؟" اجبت "اذا اردتم ذلك"
And I went away.
و ذهبت بعيداً.
About eight hours later,
بعد حوالي 8 ساعات،
we found them browsing and teaching each other how to browse.
وجدناهم يتصفحون الانترنت و يعلمون بعضهم كيف يتصفحون.
So I said, "Well that's impossible, because --
فقلت "و لكن هذا مستحيل، لأنه...
How is it possible? They don't know anything."
كيف يمكن هذا؟ فهم لا يعرفون شيئا"
My colleagues said, "No, it's a simple solution.
قال لي زميلي " الحل بسيط جداً
One of your students must have been passing by,
قد يكون انه مرّ أحد تلامذتك من هنا
showed them how to use the mouse."
و علّمهم كيف يستخدمون الفأرة"
So I said, "Yeah, that's possible."
فقلت "نعم، هذا احتمال وارد"
So I repeated the experiment. I went 300 miles out of Delhi
فقمت بإعادة التجربة. سافرت 300 ميل خارج نيو دلهي
into a really remote village
الى قرية بعيدة و معزولة
where the chances of a passing software development engineer
حيث يكون احتمال مرور مهندس حاسوب
was very little. (Laughter)
ضئيل جداً. (ضحك)
I repeated the experiment there.
أعدت التجربة هناك.
There was no place to stay, so I stuck my computer in,
لم يكن هناك مكان لأستقر به، فوضعت جهاز الحاسوب
I went away, came back after a couple of months,
ثم ذهبت و عدت بعد بضعة اشهر،
found kids playing games on it.
وجدت الاطفال يلعبون الألعاب عليه
When they saw me, they said,
و عندما رأوني قالوا لي،
"We want a faster processor and a better mouse."
"نريد معالج اسرع و فأرة افضل"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I said, "How on Earth do you know all this?"
فسألت "كيف لكم ان تعرفوا كل هذا؟"
And they said something very interesting to me.
فقالوا لي ما هو مثيراً للإهتمام
In an irritated voice, they said,
بصوت فيه بعض الانزعاج
"You've given us a machine that works only in English,
"لقد اعطيتنا آلة لا تعمل الا بالإنجليزية
so we had to teach ourselves English in order to use it." (Laughter)
فإضطررنا لتعليم انفسنا الانجليزية حتى نستطيع استخدامها" (ضحك)
That's the first time, as a teacher,
هذه أول مرة، كمعلم،
that I had heard the word "teach ourselves" said so casually.
اسمع فيها تعبير "تعليم انفسنا" يقال بشكل اعتيادي هكذا.
Here's a short glimpse from those years.
هنا لمحة بسيطة من هذه الأيام،
That's the first day at the Hole in the Wall.
هذا اول يوم في تجربة الفتحة على الحائط
On your right is an eight-year-old.
و على اليمين طفل ذو 8 اعوام
To his left is his student. She's six.
و على يساره تلميذته، ذات الـ 6 اعوام.
And he's teaching her how to browse.
و هو يعلمها كيف تتصفح.
Then onto other parts of the country,
و من ثم الى أجزاء اخرى من البلاد،
I repeated this over and over again,
لقد كررت التجربة مراراً و تكراراً
getting exactly the same results that we were.
حاصلاً على نفس النتائج في كل مرة
["Hole in the wall film - 1999"]
(فيلم الفتحة على الحائط - 1999)
An eight-year-old telling his elder sister what to do.
طفل في الثامنة يعلّم اخته الاكبر ماذا تفعل
And finally a girl explaining in Marathi what it is,
و هنا طفلة تشرح باللغة المحلية ما هذا
and said, "There's a processor inside."
و تقول "هناك معالج بالداخل"
So I started publishing.
فعندها قمت بالنشر.
I published everywhere. I wrote down and measured everything,
نشرت في كل مكان، كتبت و قمت بقياس كل شيء
and I said, in nine months, a group of children
و قلت انه خلال 9 اشهر، اذا ترك مجموعة من الاطفال
left alone with a computer in any language
وحدهم مع جهاز حاسوب، بأي لغة
will reach the same standard as an office secretary in the West.
سيصلون نفس المستوى لسكرتيرة في الغرب
I'd seen it happen over and over and over again.
لقد رأيت هذا يحدث كل مرة.
But I was curious to know, what else would they do
و لكن كان لدي فضول أن أعرف ماذا يمكن ان يفعلوا غير ذلك
if they could do this much?
اذا كان يمكنهم فعل هذا؟
I started experimenting with other subjects,
فبدأت التجربة في مواضيع أخرى،
among them, for example, pronunciation.
و منها، مثالاً، النطق.
There's one community of children in southern India
هناك مجموعة من الأطفال في جنوب الهند
whose English pronunciation is really bad,
نطقهم للإنجليزية سيء جداً،
and they needed good pronunciation because that would improve their jobs.
و كانوا يحتاجون الى تحسين النطق الذي سيحسن عملهم.
I gave them a speech-to-text engine in a computer,
أعطيتهم جهاز تحويل الكلام الى كتابة
and I said, "Keep talking into it until it types what you say."
و قلت "لا تتوقفوا عن التحدث اليه حتى يكتب ما تقولون"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They did that, and watch a little bit of this.
لفد فعلوا ذلك. شاهدوا بعض من هذا.
Computer: Nice to meet you.Child: Nice to meet you.
الجهاز: سعدت بلقائك. الطفل: سعدت بلقائك.
Sugata Mitra: The reason I ended with the face
لقد أنهيت اللقطة بوجه
of this young lady over there is because I suspect many of you know her.
هذه الطفلة الصغيرة لأني اظن ان معظمكم يعرفها.
She has now joined a call center in Hyderabad
لقد انضمت الى مركز الاتصالات بحيدراباد
and may have tortured you about your credit card bills
و يمكن انها ضايقتكم بخصوص فواتير بطاقات الإئتمان
in a very clear English accent.
بلهجة انجليزية واضحة.
So then people said, well, how far will it go?
و من ثم سأل الناس، الى اين ينتهي المطاف؟
Where does it stop?
ما هي النهاية؟
I decided I would destroy my own argument
فقررت هدم فكرتي شخصياً
by creating an absurd proposition.
بطرح عرض مبالغاً فيه
I made a hypothesis, a ridiculous hypothesis.
لقد وضعت اطروحة، اطروحة سخيفة.
Tamil is a south Indian language, and I said,
التامٍل هي لغة جنوب الهند، فقلت،
can Tamil-speaking children in a south Indian village
هل يمكن للأطفال المتحدثين بالتامِل في قرية في جنوب الهند
learn the biotechnology of DNA replication in English
تعلم تكنولوجيا نسخ الحمض النووي باللغة الانجليزية
from a streetside computer?
من حاسوب على الشارع؟
And I said, I'll measure them. They'll get a zero.
فقلت انني سأقيس مستواهم. و سيحصلون على صفر.
I'll spend a couple of months, I'll leave it for a couple of months,
سأقضي معهم بضع اشهر، ثم اذهب بعيداً لعدة اشهر
I'll go back, they'll get another zero.
ثم اعود، فيحصلون على صفر مجدداً،
I'll go back to the lab and say, we need teachers.
سأعود الى المعمل و اطلب مساعدة اساتذة.
I found a village. It was called Kallikuppam in southern India.
وجدت قرية. كانت تسمى كالِكوبم في جنوب الهند.
I put in Hole in the Wall computers there,
وضعت حواسيب فتحة على الحائط هناك،
downloaded all kinds of stuff from the Internet about DNA replication,
حمّلت كل انواع المعلومات عن نسخ الحمض النووي من الانترنت،
most of which I didn't understand.
اشياء انا شخصياً لا افهمها.
The children came rushing, said, "What's all this?"
أتى الاطفال مسرعون "ما كل هذا؟" سألوا
So I said, "It's very topical, very important. But it's all in English."
فقلت لهم "هو موضوع كبير و مهم و كله بالإنجليزية"
So they said, "How can we understand such big English words
فقالوا "كيف يمكننا فهم هذه الكلمات الانجليزية المعقدة
and diagrams and chemistry?"
و رسومات بيانية و كيمياء ؟"
So by now, I had developed a new pedagogical method,
حتى تلك اللحظة، كنت قد طورت طريقة تربوية جديدة
so I applied that. I said, "I haven't the foggiest idea."
فطبقت ذلك و قلت "ليست لدي ادنى فكرة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And anyway, I am going away."
"و على اي حال، انا ذاهب"
So I left them for a couple of months.
ثم تركتهم لبضع اشهر.
They'd got a zero. I gave them a test.
و حصلوا على صفر بعدما اعطيتهم الاختبار.
I came back after two months
عدت بعد شهرين
and the children trooped in and said, "We've understood nothing."
و احتشد على الاطفال و قالوا "لم نفهم اي شيء"
So I said, "Well, what did I expect?"
فسألت نفسي "ماذا كنت اتوقع؟"
So I said, "Okay, but how long did it take you
ثم قلت لهم "حسناً، كم من الوقت استغرق هذا
before you decided that you can't understand anything?"
قبل ان تقرروا انكم لم تفهموا شيئً؟"
So they said, "We haven't given up.
فقالوا لي "نحن لم نستسلم بعد
We look at it every single day."
فنحن ننظر اليها كل يوم"
So I said, "What? You don't understand these screens
فقلت "لماذا؟ هل لا تفهمون هذه الشاشات؟
and you keep staring at it for two months? What for?"
و تجلسون لتنظروا اليها لمدة شهرين؟ لماذا؟"
So a little girl who you see just now,
فقامت فتاة صغيرة، سترونها الآن،
she raised her hand, and she says to me in broken Tamil and English,
رفعت يدها و قالت لي في لهجة مكسورة من الانجليزي و التامل،
she said, "Well, apart from the fact that
قالت "حسناً، بجانب معلومة ان نسخ
improper replication of the DNA molecule causes disease,
الحمض النووي الغير سليم يسبب الامراض،
we haven't understood anything else."
فإننا لم نفهم اي شيء آخر"
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) ..( تصفيق)
So I tested them.
فأختبرتهم.
I got an educational impossibility, zero to 30 percent
فحصلت على معجزة تعليمية، من الصفر الى 30% تحسن.
in two months in the tropical heat
خلال شهرين تحت حرارة المنطقة الاستوائية
with a computer under the tree in a language they didn't know
مع جهاز حاسوب تحت الشجرة بلغة لا يعرفونها
doing something that's a decade ahead of their time.
يفعلون شيء سابق لزمانهم.
Absurd. But I had to follow the Victorian norm.
غير معقول. و لكن كان على ان اتبع المقياس الفكتوري.
Thirty percent is a fail.
30% ليست درجة نجاح.
How do I get them to pass? I have to get them 20 more marks.
كيف اجعلهم ينجحون؟ علي ان ادفعهم 20 درجة اخرى.
I couldn't find a teacher. What I did find was a friend that they had,
لم استطع ايجاد استاذ، و لكني وجدت صديقة لهم
a 22-year-old girl who was an accountant
و هي محاسبة تبلغ من العمر 22 عاماً
and she played with them all the time.
و كانت دائماً تلعب معهم.
So I asked this girl, "Can you help them?"
فسألتها "هل يمكنك مساعدتهم؟"
So she says, "Absolutely not.
فقالت "بالتأكيد لا
I didn't have science in school. I have no idea
"لم ادرس العلوم في المدرسة. ليست لدي فكرة
what they're doing under that tree all day long. I can't help you."
عن ما يفعلونه تحت تلك الشجرة طيلة اليوم، لا استطيع مساعدتك"
I said, "I'll tell you what. Use the method of the grandmother."
قلت لها "سأقول لك ماذا تفعلين، استخدمي اسلوب الجدة"
So she says, "What's that?"
فسألتني "و ما هذا؟"
I said, "Stand behind them.
قلت "قفي خلفهم
Whenever they do anything, you just say,
وقتما فعلوا اي شيءً، فقط تقولين،
'Well, wow, I mean, how did you do that?
"واو، اقصد كيف فعلت ذلك؟"
What's the next page? Gosh, when I was your age, I could have never done that.'
"ما هي الصفحة التالية؟ ياللهول، عندما كنت بعمرك، كان لا يمكنني فعل ذلك"
You know what grannies do."
كما تفعل الجدات"
So she did that for two more months.
ففعلت ذلك لشهرين بعد ذلك.
The scores jumped to 50 percent.
و قفزت الدرجات الى 50%.
Kallikuppam had caught up
كالكوبم التحقت بمستوى
with my control school in New Delhi,
مدرستي في نيو دلهي
a rich private school with a trained biotechnology teacher.
مدرسة للأغنياء بها استاذ علوم احياء متدرب.
When I saw that graph I knew there is a way to level the playing field.
عندما رأيت ذلك الرسم البياني، علمت ان هناك وسيلة لتطوير التنافس.
Here's Kallikuppam.
هاهي قرية كالكوبم.
(Children speaking) Neurons ... communication.
(اطفال يتحدثون) خلايا عصبية.. تواصل.
I got the camera angle wrong. That one is just amateur stuff,
لم تكن هذه افضل صورة،
but what she was saying, as you could make out,
و لكن كما قد تخمنون، كانت الطفلة تتحدث
was about neurons, with her hands were like that,
عن الخلايا العصبية، بأيديها كذلك،
and she was saying neurons communicate.
و كانت تقول ان الخلايا العصبية تتواصل.
At 12.
في سن الـ12.
So what are jobs going to be like?
اذا، فماذا سيكون شكل الوظائف؟
Well, we know what they're like today.
فنحن نعرف كيف هي اليوم.
What's learning going to be like? We know what it's like today,
كيف سيكون التعلم؟ فنحن نعلم كيف هو اليوم،
children pouring over with their mobile phones on the one hand
الاطفال ينشغلون بأجهزة المحمول بيًد
and then reluctantly going to school to pick up their books with their other hand.
و في اليد الاخرى مترددين لحمل الكتب و الذهاب الى المدرسة.
What will it be tomorrow?
كيف سيكون التعلم غداً؟
Could it be that we don't need to go to school at all?
هل يمكن ان لا نحتاج الى المدرسة نهائياً؟
Could it be that, at the point in time when you need to know something,
هل يمكن انه اذا احتجت الى اي معلومة في اي وقت
you can find out in two minutes?
يمكنك العثور عليها خلال دقيقتين؟
Could it be -- a devastating question,
هل يمكن؟ سؤال محير،
a question that was framed for me by Nicholas Negroponte --
سؤال رسمه لي نيكولاس نيقروبونتي--
could it be that we are heading towards or maybe in
هل يمكن ان نكون متجهين نحو مستقبل
a future where knowing is obsolete?
به المعرفة بائدة؟
But that's terrible. We are homo sapiens.
و لكن هذا فظيع، نحن بشر.
Knowing, that's what distinguishes us from the apes.
المعرفة، هي التي تفرقنا من الحيوانات.
But look at it this way.
و لكن لننظر اليها من هذه الزاوية.
It took nature 100 million years
استغرقت الطبيعة 100 مليون عام
to make the ape stand up
لتجعل القرد يقف مستقيماً
and become Homo sapiens.
و يصبح بشراً.
It took us only 10,000 to make knowing obsolete.
ثم استغرقنا نحن 10،000 لنجعل المعرفة بائدة.
What an achievement that is.
ياله من انجاز عظيم.
But we have to integrate that into our own future.
و لكن يجب علينا مزج كل هذا مع مستقبلنا.
Encouragement seems to be the key.
التشجيع ، يبدو ان ذلك هو المفتاح.
If you look at Kuppam,
اذا نظرتم الى كالكوبم،
if you look at all of the experiments that I did,
اذا نظرتم الى التجارب التى اجريتها،
it was simply saying, "Wow," saluting learning.
يتضح انه مجرد قول "واو"، تحيةً للتعلم.
There is evidence from neuroscience.
و هناك دليل من علم اعصاب المخ.
The reptilian part of our brain, which sits in the center of our brain,
الجزء الزاحف من عقلنا و هو واقع في المركز
when it's threatened, it shuts down everything else,
عندما يشعر بالخطر، يغلق كل شيء آخر
it shuts down the prefrontal cortex, the parts which learn,
يغلق الجزء الامامي و الجزء الذي يتعلم.
it shuts all of that down.
كل ذلك يتم اغلاقه.
Punishment and examinations are seen as threats.
العقاب و الامتحانات يُنظر اليها كالخطر.
We take our children, we make them shut their brains down,
فنحن نأخذ بآبنائنا، نجعل عقولهم تنغلق
and then we say, "Perform."
ثم نقول لهم، ادّوا الواجب.
Why did they create a system like that?
لماذا صنعوا نظاماً كهذا؟
Because it was needed.
لأنه كان ضرورياً
There was an age in the Age of Empires
في زمن الامبراطورية، كانت هناك حوجة
when you needed those people who can survive under threat.
لأناس يتعايشون مع المخاطر.
When you're standing in a trench all alone,
عند وقوفك في خندق لوحدك،
if you could have survived, you're okay, you've passed.
اذا استطعت ان تعيش، فلقد نجحت
If you didn't, you failed.
و اذا لا، فقد فشلت.
But the Age of Empires is gone.
و لكن عصر الامبراطورية انطوى.
What happens to creativity in our age?
ماذا يحدث للإبداع في زمننا هذا؟
We need to shift that balance back
علينا اعادة التوازن من الخطر
from threat to pleasure.
الى المتعة.
I came back to England looking for British grandmothers.
لقد عدت الى انجلترا باحثاً عن جدات انجليزيات.
I put out notices in papers saying,
وزعت اوراق اعلانات تقول،
if you are a British grandmother, if you have broadband and a web camera,
اذا كنت جدة انجليزية، لديك جهاز اتصال بالإنترنت و كاميرا
can you give me one hour of your time per week for free?
هل يمكنك اعطائي ساعة واحدة في الاسبوع من وقتك مجاناً؟
I got 200 in the first two weeks.
حصلت على 200 في اول اسبوعين.
I know more British grandmothers than anyone in the universe. (Laughter)
الآن اعرف عدد جدات انجليزيات اكثر من اي انسان في الكون. (ضحك)
They're called the Granny Cloud.
اسميناهم «سحابة الجدة»
The Granny Cloud sits on the Internet.
«سحابة الجدة» على الانترنت
If there's a child in trouble, we beam a Gran.
فاذا كان هناك طفل في مأزق نرسل له جدة.
She goes on over Skype and she sorts things out.
تتحدث معه على سكايب و تساعده في حل المعضلة.
I've seen them do it from a village called Diggles
لقد رأيتهم يفعلون ذلك من قرية تدعى «دجلز»
in northwestern England,
في شمال غرب انجلترا
deep inside a village in Tamil Nadu, India,
الى اعماق قرية في تامل نادو في الهند
6,000 miles away.
على مسافة 6،000 ميل.
She does it with only one age-old gesture.
فقط بتلويح قديم
"Shhh."
"ششش"
Okay?
حسناً؟
Watch this.
شاهدوا هذا.
Grandmother: You can't catch me. You say it.
الجدة: لن تستطيع القبض علي، قولوها.
You can't catch me.
لن تستطيع القبض علي
Children: You can't catch me.
الاطفال: لن تستطيع القبض علي
Grandmother: I'm the Gingerbread Man.Children: I'm the Gingerbread Man.
الجدة: انا الرجل العجيب. الاطفال: انا الرجل العجيب.
Grandmother: Well done! Very good.
الجدة: احسنتم، جيد جداَ!
SM: So what's happening here?
اذا، ماذا يحدث هنا؟
I think what we need to look at is
اعتقد ان ما يجب النظر فيه هو
we need to look at learning
التعلّم
as the product of educational self-organization.
كناتج لتنظيم التعلم الذاتي
If you allow the educational process to self-organize,
اذا سمحنا لعملية التعلم ان تحدث لوحدها
then learning emerges.
فسيولد التعليم.
It's not about making learning happen.
ليس بصنع التعليم
It's about letting it happen.
انما بترك التعلم ليحدث.
The teacher sets the process in motion
المعلمة تخلق جو التعلم
and then she stands back in awe
و من ثم تشاهد في اعجاب
and watches as learning happens.
كيف يحدث التعلم.
I think that's what all this is pointing at.
فهذا كل ما يشير اليه الكلام.
But how will we know? How will we come to know?
و لكن، كيف سنعرف؟
Well, I intend to build
حسناً، انا انوي بناء
these Self-Organized Learning Environments.
هذه البيئة التي ينشاء فيها التعلم الذاتي.
They are basically broadband, collaboration
هي ببساطة اتصال بالشبكة + تعاون + تشجيع
and encouragement put together.
يعملوا سوياً.
I've tried this in many, many schools.
لقد جربت هذا مع الكثير من المدارس
It's been tried all over the world, and teachers
لقد جربت في كل انحاء العالم، و المعلمون
sort of stand back and say, "It just happens by itself?"
يقفون في الخلف و يقولون "ان التعلم يحدث لوحده"
And I said, "Yeah, it happens by itself.""How did you know that?"
و اقول "نعم هذا صحيح". "كيف تعرف ذلك؟"
I said, "You won't believe the children who told me
اقول لهم "لن تصدقوا الاطفال الذين اخبروني
and where they're from."
و من اين جاءوا"
Here's a SOLE in action.
و هنا، ها هو نظام التعلم الذاتي «سول» يعمل
(Children talking)
(اطفال يتحدثون)
This one is in England.
هذا في انجلترا.
He maintains law and order,
انه يحافظ على النظام،
because remember, there's no teacher around.
لا تنسوا، فليس هناك معلم في المكان.
Girl: The total number of electrons is not equal to the total number of protons -- SM: Australia
طفلة: مجموع الالكترونات لا يساوي مجموع البروتونات
Girl: -- giving it a net positive or negative electrical charge.
لتعطيها صافي الموجب من الشحنات الكهربائية السالبة.
The net charge on an ion is equal to the number of protons
صافي الشحنة في الأيون يساوي عدد البروتونات
in the ion minus the number of electrons.
في الأيون ناقص عدد الالكترونات.
SM: A decade ahead of her time.
سابقة لوقتها بعقد كامل
So SOLEs, I think we need a curriculum of big questions.
اذا، اظن اننا نحتاج منهج من الأسئلة الكبيرة.
You already heard about that. You know what that means.
لقد سمعتم عن هذا و تعرفون ما يعني.
There was a time when Stone Age men and women
كان يجلس الرجال و النساء في العصر الحجري
used to sit and look up at the sky and say,
ينظرون الى السماء و يتسائلون،
"What are those twinkling lights?"
"ما هي تلك الأنوار اللامعة؟"
They built the first curriculum, but we've lost sight of those wondrous questions.
لقد بنوا اول منهج تعليمي بهذه الاسئلة المليئة بالتأمل،
We've brought it down to the tangent of an angle.
و لكننا فقدنا الرؤية و قلصناها الى مماس الزواية.
But that's not sexy enough.
و هذا ليس ممتعاً كفاية.
The way you would put it to a nine-year-old is to say,
عندما تقولها لذوي التسعة اعوام يكون السؤال،
"If a meteorite was coming to hit the Earth,
"اذا كان كويكب ليضرب الارض،
how would you figure out if it was going to or not?"
كيف نعرف اذا كان سيصيب ام لا؟"
And if he says, "Well, what? how?"
و اذا قال " كيف؟ ماذا؟"
you say, "There's a magic word. It's called the tangent of an angle,"
قل له "هناك كلمة سحرية، و هي مماس الزاوية"
and leave him alone. He'll figure it out.
و دعه و شأنه، و سيدرك الحل لوحده.
So here are a couple of images from SOLEs.
فها هنا بعض الصور من بيئة التعلم «سول»
I've tried incredible, incredible questions --
لقد جربت اسئلة رهيبة
"When did the world begin? How will it end?" —
"كيف ابتداء العالم؟ كيف سينتهي؟"
to nine-year-olds.
الى اطفال في عمر التاسعة.
This one is about what happens to the air we breathe.
هذا السؤال عن ما يحدث للهواء الذي نستنشقه.
This is done by children without the help of any teacher.
هذا من صنع اطفال من غير مساعدة اي معلم.
The teacher only raises the question,
المعلم فقط يطرح الأسئلة،
and then stands back and admires the answer.
و من ثم يقف بعيداً اعجاباً بالإجابات.
So what's my wish?
اذاً، ما هي أمنيتي؟
My wish is
أمنيتي هي
that we design the future of learning.
ان نصمم مستقبل التعلم
We don't want to be spare parts
لا نريد ان نكون قطع غيار (أجزاء)
for a great human computer, do we?
لآلة بشرية كبيرة، هل نريد ذلك؟
So we need to design a future for learning.
لذلك نحتاج ان نصمم مستقبل التعلم.
And I've got to -- hang on,
و يجب علي - انتظروا...
I've got to get this wording exactly right,
حتى يكون كلامي دقيقاً،
because, you know, it's very important.
لأنه مهم جداً، كما تعلمون.
My wish is to help design a future of learning
أمنيتي هي ان اساعد في تصميم مستقبل للتعلم
by supporting children all over the world
بمساعدة الاطفال من حول العالم
to tap into their wonder and their ability to work together.
ليدخلوا عالم خيالهم و قدرتهم على العمل سوياً.
Help me build this school.
ساعدوني في بناء هذه المدرسة.
It will be called the School in the Cloud.
سندعوها «مدرسة على السحب»
It will be a school where children go on these intellectual adventures
تكون مدرسة يخوض فيها الاطفال تلك المغامرات العلمية
driven by the big questions which their mediators put in.
تقودهم تلك الأسئلة الكبيرة التي يضعونها المعلمون.
The way I want to do this
اريد ان افعل هذا
is to build a facility where I can study this.
ببناء مكان ادرس فيه هذا المشروع
It's a facility which is practically unmanned.
مكان ليس له اسم معين
There's only one granny
و هناك جدة واحدة
who manages health and safety.
تهتم بالصحة و السلامة.
The rest of it's from the cloud.
و الباقين من السحابة.
The lights are turned on and off by the cloud,
تقفل و تفتح الانوار من السحابة
etc., etc., everything's done from the cloud.
كل شيء من السحابة.
But I want you for another purpose.
و لكني اريدكم لغرض آخر،
You can do Self-Organized Learning Environments
يمكنكم صناعة بيئة للتعلم الذاتي
at home, in the school, outside of school, in clubs.
في البيت، في المدرسة، خارج المدرسة، في النوادي.
It's very easy to do. There's a great document
سهل جداً بناءها. هناك وثيقة جيدة
produced by TED which tells you how to do it.
من انتاج TED تحدثكم عن طريقة البناء.
If you would please, please do it
اذا امكنكم، من فضلكم افعلوا ذلك.
across all five continents
في كل القارات الخمس
and send me the data,
و ارسلوا لي البيانات،
then I'll put it all together, move it into the School of Clouds,
ثم سأضعها سوياً، اضعها في مدرسة السحب
and create the future of learning.
و اصنع مستقبل التعلم.
That's my wish.
هذه هي امنيتي.
And just one last thing.
و شيء اخير،
I'll take you to the top of the Himalayas.
سأخذكم الى اعلى الهملايا
At 12,000 feet, where the air is thin,
بإرتفاع 12،000 قدم حيث ينخفض الهواء،
I once built two Hole in the Wall computers,
لقد وضعت حاسوب فتحة على الحائط ذات مرة،
and the children flocked there.
و هرعوا اليه الاطفال.
And there was this little girl who was following me around.
و كانت هناك طفلة صغيرة تتبعني حيثما ذهبت
And I said to her, "You know, I want to give a computer to everybody, every child.
و قلت لها "هل تعلمين، اريد ان اعطي جهاز حاسوب لكل شخص و لكل طفل
I don't know, what should I do?"
لا اعلم، ماذا افعل؟"
And I was trying to take a picture of her quietly.
و كنت احاول ان التقط لها صورة بهدوء
She suddenly raised her hand like this, and said to me,
فجأةَ رفعت يدها و قالت لي
"Get on with it."
"فلتفعل ذلك و لا تتوقف"
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) .. (تصفيق)
I think it was good advice.
اظنها كانت نصيحة جيدة
I'll follow her advice. I'll stop talking.
سأتبعها و سأكف عن الكلام.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
شكراً، شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً، شكراً. (تصفيق).
Thank you very much. Wow. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً. (تصفيق).